Register of the Glen S. Taylor papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Glen S. Taylor papers
1942-1983
1951-1953
85047
Hoover Institution Archives
1 manuscript box (0.4 linear feet)
The Glen S. Taylor papers consist of notes, memoranda, correspondence, reports, press releases, and printed matter relating to various aspects of North Atlantic Treaty Organization (NATO) activities.
Taylor, Glen S.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1985.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
Director, Office of Statistics, North Atlantic Treaty Organization, 1951-1953.
Scope and Content of Collection
The majority of the materials in the Glen S. Taylor papers relate to his tenure as the Director of Statistics for the North Atlantic Treaty Organization (NATO) from 1951 to 1953. These include notes, meeting summaries, memoranda, correspondence, reports, press releases, and printed matter on administrative topics such as NATO's staff and organization, as well as the broader themes of NATO's role and objectives. Also included in the collection are photographs and an embassy pass from London, 1942.
The original chronological arrangement of the papers has been maintained, though the groupings of materials were created by the archivist.
North Atlantic Treaty Organization.; Europe--Defenses.
- Personal File, 1942, 1951-1953
  - Photographs, circa 1942 (Box-folder 1: 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    Black and white photographs of London depicting buildings and the destruction caused by German bombing of the city.
  - Embassy pass and driver's license, 1942, 1952 (Box-folder 1: 2)
  - Calendars, 1951-1953 (Box-folder 1: 3)
    Includes handwritten notes regarding appointments.
  - Notes, circa 1951-1953 (Box-folder 1: 4)
    Handwritten notes, some of which may relate to Taylor's work with NATO, though most seem to address travel arrangements and reservations.
- NATO File, 1951-1962, 1983
  - Chronological file, 1951-1954
    Correspondence, memoranda, reports, press releases, and handwritten notes.
    - 1951 (Box-folder 1: 5)
    - 1952 (Box-folder 1: 6)
    - 1953 (Box-folder 1: 7)
    - 1954, 1959-1962 (Box-folder 1: 8)
      Includes press releases and charts relating to defense expenditures of NATO countries.
  - Press cuttings, 1951-1953, 1983 (Box-folder 1: 9)
    With the exception of one clipping from the Wall Street Journal (1983), the clippings are from European publications (1951-1953).
  - Printed matter, 1952-1962 (Box-folder 1: 10)
    Arrangement Statement
    Arranged chronologically by date of publication.
    - Atlantic Alliance: NATO's Role in the Free World, a report by a Study Group of the Royal Institute of International Affairs, 1952
    - The NATO Handbook: Why the Treaty Was Signed, What the Treaty Says, How NATO Works, NATO Information Service, 1952 January 1
    - The North Atlantic Treaty Organization: A Brief Account of the Development of NATO and an Analysis of Its Present Structure, NATO Information Service, 1952 December
    - The NATO Handbook: Why the Treaty Was Signed, What the Treaty Says, How the Organization Developed (two copies), NATO Information Service, 1953
    - "April 1952 to April 1957," NATO Letter, Vol. 5, special supplement to No. 6, 1957 June
    - "A Report on the North Atlantic Treaty Organization," Kyra Taylor, 1957 June 3
      An assignment for a U.S. History class written by Glen Taylor's daughter.
    - The NATO Handbook, sixth ed., NATO Information Service, 1958
    - Why NATO?, Paul-Henri Spaak, Secretary-General of NATO, 1959
    - "Ten Years of Atlantic Co-operation, 1949-1959," NATO Letter, special issue, circa 1959
    - "Essential Values of Western Civilization," Lester B. Pearson, circa 1959
    - Vigilance: The Price of Liberty, NATO Information Service, 1960
    - "The Western European Union and NATO Problems,", circa 1962
- Declassified U.S. Government Records, 1951-1953
  Formerly security-classified records of the U.S. government, released in full or in part. Includes some interfiled, unclassified government records. Arranged chronologically by date of release, thereunder chronologically by date of creation.
  - 2016 February release of records, 1951-1953 (Box-folder 1: 11)
    Memoranda, reports, notes, and correspondence relating to Taylor's work with NATO, originally from the chronological file. Includes report on "Production and Supply Planning," as well as summaries of meetings with various delegations.